[Music]
Thomas thank you very much for making
the time to speak to me you wrote an
article that was incredibly well
researched I think it was about 39 pages
in total that has been very very popular
I think I've been shared over 24 million
times now in the last few days would you
just be able to sort of summarize what
do you think is the main takeaway from
that article that people need to know
yes sure the number of cases of coroner
virus is exploding globally people don't
realize that's happening because this is
exponential which means that at the
beginning it's very slow and suddenly it
explodes that is why most countries have
not taking the measures that they needed
to take the moment to take the measures
it's when it's here it's not only it's
here at that point the outbreak has
already exploded so what you need so the
author of the article was to explain
what's going to happen which is if you
don't do anything the cases are going to
explode once they explode they're going
to overrun the healthcare system once
they do the mortality rate of the
coroner virus will explode probably up
to 10x 10 times higher mortality plus
all the other comorbidities meaning that
if you have a heart attack but the ICU
is collapsed you're gonna die
and so what are we to do against to do
the to prevent that from happening
reduce our social contact as much as
possible it's called social distancing
so that instead of having a huge spike a
huge peak we little by little increase
this illness so that a we don't overrun
the healthcare system and me as many
people as possible can have it not today
but in a year and a year and a half when
there's gonna be vaccine
Thomas can I ask your your background
because I understand you
in the media not a journalist how long
have to meet you to write and what's
your background for doing this so I had
spent before I wrote it I had spent
around two weeks researching this around
for four to five hours a day and I think
your underlying question is why should
people listen to me
and I think the answer is they shouldn't
they shouldn't listen to me I I am NOT
in the PDL module just I'm not a
biologist what I've done is gather all
the research from all these different
places and put it in one place so that
people can understand it you should
judge the article based on the data and
the arguments and sources not on the
fact that it's me it so happens that I
have a couple of background elements
that have helped me put this together
I'm an engineer I have two masters of
science so I'm very very close to all
things data analysis and statistics I
worked as a consultant where I had to
get into companies and understand them
within two to three weeks so I'm very I
have experience going deep into
understanding a problem very very
quickly
I also created some viral applications
that exploded to up to 20 million users
so I am acquainted with the analytics of
virality I think these are some of the
reasons why I was able to put these two
together but people shouldn't see me as
the person making the arguments but
rather making the Assembly of the
arguments and so we talk a lot on on
this channel we look very closely at
sense-making
what are the failures in sense-making
and especially about how do we get
better how do we up regulate our
discernment and our sense making and
it's really interesting that you seem to
be doing something that so far the
mainstream media hasn't done to that
level why do you think that is well the
median and
and politicians and and and I care about
both but I came more about politicians I
think I think one of the key mental
frameworks that most people are lack is
exponential growth the the my job I
didn't mention that in but in my job
both in the viral applications but but
in tech in general you're going for
exponential growth and you understand
the mechanics of exponents for growth so
when you see that something is growing
at 20% percent or 30 percent day over
day you freak out you're super happy if
it's your product or you're super super
super scared if it's a virus but because
you understand what's gonna happen you
know week two weeks three weeks three
months four months so I think that's
what that's one of the key issues why
people didn't understand what was going
to happen there's also an issue of
connecting the dots here because it's
not just one part this is a puzzle and
you need to pull it together and most
journalists especially when they're
covering news they are not trained to
put all the pieces together I mean this
is you need to put the pieces together
of hey this is not China anymore it's
these other countries hey it's gonna be
growing exponentially hey the only way
to stop this is with social distancing
and so on and so forth so a lot of
journalists do that really well but it's
these are usually like research pieces
that take months not not any news cycle
that's my guess I have no idea here I
think on the politician side my guess is
and again it is a guess they they are
making decisions with an unclear
understanding of what the objective is
and what the cost benefits are and I'll
give an example right now you have a
country that just friends that just said
that they're going to be doing heavy
social distancing and you have another
one the UK which is saying that we're
gonna have herd immunity you know
it sounds crazy that two countries are
so close to each other geographically
and are only a part in a few days in the
number of cases have a drastically
different decision-making process right
and my guess is by hearing different
people in these different countries is
that they're not talking apples to
apples in the British government they're
saying oh it's too expensive it's too
hard to make to do social distancing so
let's just run this thing slow it down a
little bit but run this the French are
saying oh and we realize now this is bad
that's let's slow this down as much as
possible but really the question that
both of these should be asking is what
is our objective
do we want to minimize deaths do we want
to minimize the ROI of eight years lived
versus cost of year lived and then and
then what are the measures that have the
highest cost benefit so for example for
it might be that doing a lock down right
now
for two weeks and then slowly releasing
social distancing measures has the
optimal alright because it gets your
curve it stops your curve starts going
down and when you are you're going down
you can slowly release social distancing
measures so that it's controlled right
but for you to make that decision of
whether you want to do this or like in
the UK this right you need to understand
what's the cost of was the benefit that
each one of these measures is gonna get
you versus was the cost for example
maybe eliminating all sports and gives
you a reduction of 10% in the
transmission rate and that's what you
want you want to reduce the transmission
rate by 60 percent okay so I'm gonna
stop sports because the cost is low and
then maybe I'm stopping gatherings of
100 big or more because that's super
spreading and and the cost is low and so
on and so forth and you start taking the
measures they're the lowest cost and the
highest benefit and you and you and you
add them up to get to the
to run our I i I've been looking online
for anything like this and I've not seen
anybody mention anything like this so
the fear is that they're making a
decision based on incomplete data
because based on the wrong mental
frameworks and that's why it's so half a
third in every country is making
different decisions and there there's a
lot of concern as well about the
second-order and third-order effects of
these kind of measures is there not a
concern that by implementing really
really strict social distancing really
really strict restrictions now that that
will could cascade into major like major
economic failure and and some some
effects that are potentially even worse
than the the outbreak absolutely and so
and I think that's what should be baked
into that cost benefit and so but but
that benefit doesn't exist so they're
making those decisions intuitively here
are a couple of thoughts that I think
and can can help us make these kind of
decisions you have a good example of
Wuhan or the entire Bay region where
they were extremely extremely aggressive
that and and they can understand from
there where weather second and third or
problems and there were many people were
locked home and died because of that
right but then you can see something
like Italy which is not too far away but
much better I think because the hardest
costs are things like I can go to the
hospital I can go to the groceries you
know I can't just leave home if I
absolute for example if I absolutely
have to go to work otherwise I'm gonna
lose my job then yeah you should go be
able to go to work right so it's not
these binary thing you can keep it's
more of of all the rainbow of options of
social distancing which ones are the
ones that have the highest cost benefit
right then you stack rank them and you
go all like you you say approved
approved yes yes yes yes yes no no no no
no this is the threshold based on the
optimal ROI
and are you concerned because it seems
from from here we're based in London
that the us give and you have a kind of
very individualist attitude to
healthcare you don't really have a
National Health Service you've got very
low safety nets compared to Europe so
people maybe who are sick will be more
encouraged to go into work because
they're they're closer to they don't
have sick pay
they don't have medical insurance are
you concerned that the u.s. might be
more fragile than than other places
I think this pros and cons in each
country and I'm closer to you to us and
then to Spain in France so I can compare
Europe with us that way first yes
there's no fear all sick leave
maybe we'll don't have insurance so the
contacts has the health care system as a
result a lot of people will just not be
able to stop working and will not be
able to go to the healthcare system all
right so so so these are some of the big
issues there's many more another one is
is the healthcare system being
completely privatized cannot be easily
coordinated at a national level France
for example is just showing the immense
benefits of that coordination within 24
hours they were able to to to get the
country prepared for this the US has a
few other things that are going for them
first is the density it is a very low
density country compared to most other
countries in Europe most countries in
Europe and that's great for a lower
transmission level public transport is
very bad which is great in this yoke
resistance most people take their cars
that reduces the transmission in in
public transport remote work I think is
relatively developed for white collar
workers so I think that can help and as
a rule of thumb they're a bit more
individualistic so so the social
transmission is probably gonna be lower
finally the healthcare system the good
thing about being decentralized is that
you have a lot of different approaches
to this and and the the ones that are
not as good can quick
learn from the ones very good we're
seeing a lot of systemic fragilities in
various different areas and one of them
is the ability to make sense of the
crisis and I think one of the things
that's required is for people to to
improve their discernment to step up and
potentially alternatives to some of the
failing systems are emerging and I would
put you in that bracket as someone who
seems to be making sense of the outbreak
better than most if not all in the
mainstream media who sense that that
people are having to step up so first on
my case I think these was just like
there was a lot of luck here involves a
lot of people were putting a lot of
things together and mine happen to
resonate and but I'm sure there's other
pieces that are at least as good if not
better but mine just happened to to to
catch on and this is where we are I
think here we are in a perfect example
of new information coming to society it
reminds me for example what happened
with with black seeds or the Trump
election in 2016 where it took everybody
back nobody knew how to interpret that
situation right and so suddenly there's
these new information in the system and
and and the system just doesn't know how
to cope with it and so it tries to
digest it so the question becomes when
you have these this doesn't happen
frequently by the way but but but when
it happens what is the best process to
to process this information as quickly
as possible and I would say what is
happening today is the right way to do
it
in if you think about it two weeks ago
in in the West nobody was thinking this
is a problem and then within two weeks
everybody now realizes the problem and
then and I might have contributed a
little bit to the conversation many
others have a more a lot more than than
I have but these distribution off of the
thoughts process through Twitter through
Facebook through all social media makes
gives a huge ability for our
open societies to react now this is just
one this is just one way that societies
can react I think that's the Western
world the other approach obviously is
the Chinese approach right and I think
there there's two differences to make
one of them is what happened at the
beginning of the crisis in China and
then what happened afterwards they
didn't catch it properly they didn't
catch it properly not because people
didn't alert the system but because the
system does not allow for free speech
they had people saying hey there's a
problem here there's a problem here and
these people were going to prison and
until then they realized that that the
prom was big and then they reacted
properly so I think what that
illustrates is the fact that for
understanding the problems and for
deciding to react to them societies with
free speech are going to always be
substantially stronger for decisions
quick and Swift decisions on what to do
about it then it really depends
you-you-you do have a dictatorship or a
very strong government of Praetorian
government in China who was able to to
react very quickly but Singapore and
Taiwan were also able to react very
quickly so I I don't buy the argument
that original regimes can react more
quickly I think there's a vast component
of education and culture that that is
very important here we can do better
than this week and and and Taiwan and
Singapore are an even Japan and Korea
are good examples of that can you
recommend anyone any good resources for
information for people to follow do the
people on Twitter or communities that
you think you're doing good sense making
around this yeah so so I think
a few world of meters is great for live
update on the corner virus data then
there's a github repository for raw data
on cases deaths and things like that
it's on my medium post the full link and
I like going to the raw data because an
editorial eyes because otherwise it's
very hard to tell what's right and
what's wrong
the second type of source is scientific
papers and pages like MedX for example
you can find a lot of them there's I
think around a hundred papers that
having published just this week and
coronavirus and it's growing very very
fast many of them have not been
peer-reviewed but but the point of the
reason why scientific papers are super
useful is because they are the best
thought-through package around a single
idea and so you can then take those and
incorporate them as you get more
information in comparing incorporating
that you are thinking and then there's a
few so I think that's look that's the
the core layer the core layer is the the
raw data and we always need to go back
to that and then there's the the
decorators on top of it and there's I
think that there's there's millions that
are super useful there I think for me
I'm looking right now a couple of them
that were useful so doctormick name is
mooji civic it's at mu g ec e VI k she's
a virology clinician and researcher
these things in your article or are you
able to share them with me after the
call and we can put them into the show
notes maybe I was good I'll do that
let's do that and then I can put them
into the show notes for people just a
couple of questions did you listen to
the recent Sam Harris podcast with the
with the person from Johns Hopkins no I
having this this was one of the
epidemiologists at Johns Hopkins who was
in charge of the infectious diseases and
was tasked with kind of being aware of
these outbreaks they were convinced that
the death rate was going to be maximum
0.6% whereas your article seems to be
sort of pointing at a much higher death
rate than that I wanted a wrench that
goes from actually zero six to four
and I think there's two things to to
discuss about that the key one is the
more time we read rate is not a thing
that is only depending on the virus
there are many many factors that
determine the death rate the average
death rate and one of them is just the
age of the population right one that at
least in China the death rate for people
80 and above these 15% and people much
younger 14 below I think is 0-2 on
average right so if you have a very old
opposition like Japan your mortality
rate is gonna be substantially higher
than in Nigeria so that's one of the
factors another factor is your
denominator right how many diagnostics
you have because if you because it's
very likely that you're gonna catch the
deaths somebody that dies because of
this you're probably gonna me do a test
and it's gonna it's gonna be positive
but when somebody just has a cough and
you don't test that person they might
have a concurrent virus you don't you
don't know right so the countries that
test more are going to have a lower
mortality rate and fatality rate because
of that right so so and then a third
factor is healthcare system collapse so
so for example I think in I don't
remember the actual the specific numbers
but I think in the who Bay Area the the
fatality rate is probably gonna be close
to four or five something of that
whereas outside of who Bay is gonna be
close to close to 0-9 I think right why
because the system collapsed in hubei
and I didn't outside so whatever all of
this is saying is there's a very broad
range of of fatality rates
and the question becomes what is it
going to be true form for us and so the
the first factor is is as I mention
right test rates and the US for example
is very very very low the UK is very
very very very low I think the UK is ten
times lower than South Korea as a per
capita basis and the the u.s. is even
lower as of today whereas of a couple
days ago so that's one the the other
more important one is our health care
system and that completely depends on
our response so if we take it now and we
slow it down we will and we control you
like South Korea has yes if there's a
very high chance that it's zero six
percent if we don't and the system
collapses it's much more likely that
we're going to be like wait so it's on
us it's not a thing it's on us and how
react and that's why I think it's so
important to to take measures now to
reduce the mortality rate and so the UK
has as you said before taking a
different angle they're talking about
herd immunity and managing the outbreak
and in a different way to elsewhere I'm
guessing that you're quite skeptical of
that as a strategy
so I'm yes but so I think
epidemiologists are not great at
communication unfortunately so I don't
want to put a straw man argument I want
to do the other way I want to do a steel
men argument right let's let's try to
understand really what they're trying to
say and then why I think they're wrong I
think what they're saying is look this
is very very hard to contain and so what
we need to do is is spray it over time
as much as we can to to get people
little by little yeah
infected and then immunized so that at
some point in the future a first because
it was little by little the health care
system doesn't doesn't break and be over
time these people are now immune so the
transmission rate goes down and then
this virus dies on itself and so I think
that argument is is what I think they're
making and it's a reasonable one here
are the flaws that I see with it first
is they're not accounting for the active
the fact that the vaccine is gonna come
in a year to year and a half right so in
fact if you can slow down as much as
possible this thing for up to a year to
a year and a half in fact a lot of
people who would catch it will will
wouldn't catch it at all and so they
would survive right I think that's the
first thing that's the second thing that
is crucial is that reasoning is valid
but it also means that you need to make
to take action now if you don't take
action now you're gonna have a massive
peak and your argument of flooding the
curve and spreading the cases over time
is not a revalued anymore and that is to
me the specific area where they're there
their reasoning is flawed if they're
saying herd immunity slowly then they
need to make an take action right now
not tomorrow not on Monday in to make
action right now so we use suggesting
that the the social distancing will need
to be in place for until the vaccine
arrives for a year year and a half so
yes but that said that like that it
suggests that social distancing is a
binary thing is there it's it's either
there is social distancing or there's
not and that's not true what we need to
do is right now do a lot of social
distancing to get this thing as low as
possible as fast as possible and once
that dies down they're still gonna be a
few cases here and there but then we can
release the social distancing measures
slowly so that the virus now starts
spreading again but slowly and
full way so that our healthcare system
can learn from it can increase its
capacity and and then we can play with
these things the more we understand them
the better right is there going to be no
Premier League for a year well mmm if
that's the biggest thing that
contributes to to the viral spread yeah
maybe that's not so bad it's not for
that for the clubs but it's not so bad
for the rest of us of society right
should we all stop going to groceries
right now no absolutely not
schools what about schools right so so
these are but these are the decisions
that need to be made it's not social
distancing yes or not is a hundred
things that contribute to transfer to
transmission why are the ones that we
should be still doing today and the ones
that we should stop and what is that why
it's true today and how does not evolve
over time and what do you what what's
the most likely trajectory of this from
what you've seen
going forward I guess so it all depends
on what it what actions are taken now
but but what are you what are you saying
longer-term what are your fears and what
do you thinks the best case it depends
completely on the country and and how
each country reacts let's see let's
let's do a worst case and then a best
case worst case a lot of these countries
don't react and then it's an epidemic
everywhere the the countries that want
to be protected will shut down their
their their borders for a very long time
flights are not going to be available
for a very long time between these
countries there's going to be heavy
heavy social distancing measures in the
countries that that are taking this
seriously and that will last up till
when we have vaccine in one year to year
half the that's the worst case scenario
the the best case scenario is every
country realizes very very quickly
learning from each other that this is
very serious
and they all take social distancing
measures right now therefore lowering
massively the the transmission rates
today and lowering in the next so that
would mean that we would have a peak in
cases in a couple of weeks and then it
would start slowing down so you do a
heavy social distancing for four to six
weeks this thing goes down dramatically
everywhere and then you start across the
world
releasing the the social distancing
measures there's one more thing I want
to add here is we've talked about social
distancing but social distancing is is
one of the key levers to affect
transmission but it's not the only one
so if you think about it right how does
transition this transition this
transmission rate work it depends on how
many people you meet every day and what
percentage of those meetings become a
contagion social distancing plays
against the first factor it reduces the
number of people you meet it doesn't
play as much in the contagion between
people so that's the second lever that
we can massively be using over over the
next year so for example when people say
stop handshaking doesn't notice that
that is that can be considered in social
distancing a factor but it's not as much
I'm gonna need fewer people it's if I
meet them I mean there's gonna be less
contagion right so things like I'm gonna
work at least from a distance of a
couple of meters from you I'm not gonna
shake your hands I'm gonna be wearing
masks I'm going to learn not to touch
with my face I'm gonna learn to wash my
hands every 20 minutes and so on and so
forth all these measures are not as much
social distancing but they also
dramatically reduce the transmission
rate and these are actually not as
expensive so I think though in my very
well be that you can reduce by half the
transmission rate with this and then
this is not a dramatic epidemic anymore
all right so as
society over the next few weeks we need
to learn what are these levers to reduce
the transmission rate some of them are
going social distancing some of them
reducing the contagion per per encounter
and and together figure out the the way
to not collapse healthcare systems and
and optimize both mortality rates and
the economy right
thank you very much Thomas and yeah
thank you for the work that you're
putting in in trying to track this and
make sense of it and for making the time
to speak to me I'm training holiness
thank you thank you for having me and
listening to to my thoughts
[Music]